A Guide to the James H. Newman Papers,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
James H. Newman Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-18/2/1.071
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was formerly accessioned as MSS 6852 when transferred from the Office of University Dean on Junee 30, 1962. They were transferred to the University Archives on Januaryuary 18, 2007 and given an archives record group number.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the papers of the Dean of Students (formerly known as the Dean of the University), ca. 2,100 items (7 Hollinger boxes, ca. 3 linear feet). ca. 1946-1950, the administrative files of the Dean of Students, James H. Newman and the Dean of Students Committee, headed by H.M. Hite in place after 1949 December.
These papers include correspondence with students explaining the reasons for their absence from Convocation or other behaviors (especially in the miscellaneous alphabetical folders); correspondence of various University committees that deal with student affairs, like the Bad Check Committee, the Chaperone Committee, Honor Committee, and WUVA Radio Committee; correspondence about student publications including Corks and Curls, Spectator/Crust, College Topics, and The Cavalier Daily; correspondence with President Colgate Darden, Jr.; salary and invoice files; files on student dance societies, which include the P.K. and German Club; reports or questions from other colleges, including Hollins College, Longwood College, Mary Baldwin College, Mary Washington College, Randolph Macon Women's College, and Sweet Briar College, about student misbehavior; correspondence from women seeking the non-existent position of "house mother" at the University of Virginia; and student organizations, including the Jefferson Society, T.I.L.K.A., and Washington Literary Society.
Arrangement
These files are arranged in a single series in alphabetical order according the original order of the collection.
Contents List
- "A" Miscellaneous, 1947 May-1950 March (Box-folder 1:1)
- Alumni Association, Director J. Malcolm Luck, 1946 November-1949 December (Box-folder 1:2)
- "B" Miscellaneous, 1947 February-1949 December (Box-folder 1:3)
- Bad Check Committee, 1946 October-1950 April (Box-folder 1:4)
- "Biopsy" Medical School Publication, 1946 December-1947 September (Box-folder 1:5)
- Board of Visitors-Student Affairs Committee, 1946 November-1950 May (Box-folder 1:6)
- Buildings and Grounds, 1947 September-1950 May (Box-folder 1:7)
- "C" Miscellaneous, 1946 December-1950 May (Box-folder 1:8)
- Cavalier Daily/College Topics, 1946 December-1950 May (Box-folder 1:9)
- Chaperone Committee, 1946 July-1949 November (Box-folder 1:10)
- Concert Series, Tuesday Evening, 1948 November-December (Box-folder 1:11)
- Corks and Curls, 1947 May-December (Box-folder 1:12)
- Counseling and Testing (Virginia Center), 1949 June-August (Box-folder 1:13)
- Counselors, 1950 February (Box-folder 2:1)
- "D" Miscellaneous, 1946 October-1949 April (Box-folder 2:2)
- Dance Societies, 1946 July-1949 September (Box-folder 2:3)
- Darden, Colgate W. Jr., 1947 January-1950 April (Box-folder 2:4)
- Dean of Students' Office, 1948 April-1950 June (Box-folder 2:5)
- "E" Miscellaneous, 1946 April-1949 March (Box-folder 2:6)
- Employment Folder, 1949 May-1950 May (Box-folder 2:7)
- Employment Folder, 1947 November-1949 April (Box-folder 2:8)
- "F" Miscellaneous, 1946 October-1949 May (Box-folder 2:9)
- "G" Miscellaneous, 1946 July-1949 September (Box-folder 2:10)
- "H" Miscellaneous, 1946 July-1949 November (Box-folder 3:1)
- Hollins College, 1948 February-1950 January (Box-folder 3:2)
- Honor Committee, 1945 November-1950 June (Box-folder 3:3)
- Housemothers, 1946 March-1950 July (Box-folder 3:4)
- "I" Miscellaneous, 1946 September-1949 October (Box-folder 3:5)
- Intramural Sports, 1946 August-1948 November (Box-folder 3:6)
- Invoices, 1949 July-1950 June (Box-folder 3:7)
- Invoices, 1949 January-June (Box-folder 3:8)
- Invoices, 1948 July-December (Box-folder 3:9)
- Invoices, 1947 July-1948 June (Box-folder 4:1)
- Invoices, 1946 March-1947 June (Box-folder 4:2)
- "J" Miscellaneous, 1946 October-1949 July (Box-folder 4:3)
- Jefferson Society, 1946 September-1948 January (Box-folder 4:4)
- "K" Miscellaneous, 1947 April-1950 March (Box-folder 4:5)
- "L" Miscellaneous, 1946 April-1949 September (Box-folder 4:6)
- Lewis, Ivey F., Dean of the College, 1948 January-1950 May (Box-folder 4:7)
- Lewis, Ivey F., Dean of the College, 1947 January-December (Box-folder 4:8)
- Longwood College, 1948 February-1949 April (Box-folder 4:9)
- "M" Miscellaneous, 1946 September-1950 April (Box-folder 4:10)
- Mary Baldwin College, 1948 February-1949 October (Box-folder 4:11)
- Mary Washington College, 1948 February-1949 May (Box-folder 4:12)
- Medical Interfraternity Council, 1948 January-1949 December (Box-folder 5:1)
- Mimeograph Letters, 1949 June-1950 April (Box-folder 5:2)
- Mimeograph Letters, 1947 March-1948 October (Box-folder 5:3)
- "N" Miscellaneous, 1946 April-1949 December (Box-folder 5:4)
- National Fraternity Liquor Regulations, 1947 December (Box-folder 5:5)
- National Interfraternity Council, 1946 May-1949 April (Box-folder 5:6)
- "O" Miscellaneous, 1948 July-October (Box-folder 5:7)
- "P" Miscellaneous, 1947 March-1949 October (Box-folder 5:8)
- "Palmer, Dr. Alexander M."-Near East Foundation and New York Southern Society Swindle Cases, 1949 January-October (Box-folder 5:9)
- "The Philadelphia Story"-Damage to Philadelphia Hotels, etc by University Students during the Virginia-Penn Football Game, 1947 December, 1949 October-November (Box-folder 5:10)
- "Q" Miscellaneous, 1947 April-1948 September (Box-folder 5:11)
- "R" Miscellaneous, 1946 April-1949 November (Box-folder 5:12)
- Requisitions-Purchase Orders, 1946 June-1950 March (Box-folder 6:1)
- Randolph Macon Women's College, 1948 February-1949 April (Box-folder 6:2)
- Rushton, Dr. Peters, Assistant Dean, 1948 April-1949 January (Box-folder 6:3)
- "S-Sn" Miscellaneous, 1946 April-1949 October (Box-folder 6:4)
- "So-St" Miscellaneous, 1946 August-1949 October (Box-folder 6:5)
- Selling Permits "B-W," 1948-1949 (Box-folder 6:6)
- Shea, Vincent, Bursar, 1946 July-1949 November (Box-folder 6:7)
- Spectator/Crust, 1947 May-August (Box-folder 6:8)
- Stealing, 1946 September-1949 November (Box-folder 6:9)
- Student Health Department, 1946-1949 February (Box-folder 6:10)
- Student Union, 1946 January-1949 October (Box-folder 6:11)
- Summer Quarter, 1948 April-1949 September (Box-folder 6:12)
- Sweet Briar College, 1946 April-1950 January (Box-folder 6:13)
- "T" Miscellaneous, 1946 December-1949 September (Box-folder 6:14)
- T.I.L.K.A. Society, 1947 April (Box-folder 6:15)
- Travel Expense Reimbursement Vouchers, 1946 March-1949 November (Box-folder 6:16)
- "U" Miscellaneous, 1942 May-1948 April (Box-folder 7:1)
- "V" Miscellaneous, 1947 April-1950 February (Box-folder 7:2)
- Veteran Loans "A-E," 1948-1949 (Box-folder 7:3)
- Veteran Loans "F-K," 1948-1949 (Box-folder 7:4)
- Veteran Loans "L-S," 1948-1949 (Box-folder 7:5)
- Veteran Loans "T-Z," 1948-1949 (Box-folder 7:6)
- "W" Miscellaneous, 1947 February-1949 October (Box-folder 7:7)
- Washington Literary Society, 1949 January-February (Box-folder 7:8)
- WUVA, Radio Committee, 1947 March-1949 October (Box-folder 7:9)
- "Y" Miscellaneous, 1947 March-1949 April (Box-folder 7:10)
- YMCA, 1946 August-1949 December (Box-folder 7:11)
- "Z" Miscellaneous, 1947 February-1949 September (Box-folder 7:12)